<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Breaking Bytes - Productivity</title><link href="https://breakingbytes.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://breakingbytes.github.io/feeds/productivity.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://breakingbytes.github.io/</id><updated>2023-07-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>My personal blog about &lt;a rel="me" href="https://fosstodon.org/@mikofski"&gt;me&lt;/a&gt;</subtitle><entry><title>Climbing Life Lessons: Reassessing Changing Risk</title><link href="https://breakingbytes.github.io/climbing-life-lessons-reassessing-changing-risk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Mikofski</name></author><id>tag:breakingbytes.github.io,2023-07-14:/climbing-life-lessons-reassessing-changing-risk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Reassessing risk as conditions change is critical in the backcountry.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="reassessing-risk-in-mountians"&gt;Reassessing Risk in Mountians&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.supertopo.com/rock-climbing/Yosemite-Valley-Half-Dome-Snake-Dike"&gt;Snake Dike&lt;/a&gt;
is on the southwest shoulder of Half Dome, perhaps the most recognizable rock face in
Yosemite Valley. Although considered a moderate climb, rated 5.7 R, it's sometimes called
"Snake Hike" because it's a serious commitment with huge exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Approach" src="images/P2010025.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding risk on Snake Dike is important. This climb requires planning, good timing,
a bit of skill, and lots of luck. More importantly though, you need to be constantly
aware of changing conditions, how they can affect your risk, and whether bailing is still
an easy option. Evaluating risk is one of climbing's life lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Rainout" src="images/P2010019.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snake Dike is an all day climb. The approach is a 6 mile, 3-hour hike up 2500-ft that starts
at Happy Isles behind Curry Village and follows the Mist Trail, one of my favorites.
Unfortunately, our 4am start was quickly foiled by rain, but our good timing gave us some
flexibility, so we decided to wait it out for at least an hour and then reassess. Lucky for us
our patience was rewarded, and within the hour we were back on the trail. We decided to pick up
the pace a bit to make up for the lost time. Getting caught in a thunderstrom can have deadly
consequences for climbers, so even though there was no rain in the forecast that day, we didn't
know if the weather would turn bad again later that afternoon. Same as for climbers, descending
the cables from Half Dome in a thunderstorm is a death sentence. We also didn't want to hike out
in the dark, although we had brought our torches and some emergency overnight gear just in case.
There's always trade offs to consider in the backcountry, so we tried to pack as lightly as we
could to move fast yet still be safe. There's a saying in the mountains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speed is saftey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It means don't waste time, so we didn't. Ok, well maybe we stopped to take a few photos of the
breathtaking views near Lost Lake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Photo Opp" src="images/P2010026.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had climbed Snake Dike once before with a large group of experienced climbers, and I'd been on the
Mist Trail numerous times, so I had good intuition for finding the right path to turn off the trail,
and miraculously we nailed the approach. We ate a quick snack, tied on our climbing shoes, strapped
on our harnesses, clipped on a light rack (mostly slings &amp;amp; quickdraws), and tackled the first pitch
which is actually one of the 5.7 cruxes of the climb. The "R" stands for "runout" which means there's
no protection. That pretty much describes most of Snake Dike, but the first pitch is especially gnarly.
It starts on typical Yosemite glacial polish with tiny microedges that you can friction climb up to a
roof where you can finally place your first solid piece and exhale a huge sigh of relief. If you slip on
this slab, you'll get some serious scrapes as you tumble back to the base of the climb. In researching
for this blog, I read an
&lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/yose/blogs/rescue-from-near-snake-dike-half-dome.htm"&gt;incident report from YOSAR&lt;/a&gt;
about a couple that were off route but slipped on similar frictiony slab, tumbled to the base, and
dragged the belayer, who was not clipped to anything, off her ledge and into a talus field. She had a
punctured lung, a fractured pelvis, and broke two vertebra. Climbing can be especially dangerous if
you're unlucky, don't  take precautions, and fail to assess your risk carefully. I'm not trying to
scare you, lots of things are dangerous, that's why it's important to know your risk and make conscious
decisions. Anyway, I pulled the roof, shimmied up to the ledge and made the only anchor with pro I'd
need during the entire climb. From there on out is was bolt city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike First Anchor" src="images/P2010027.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the SERENE anchor, a cordelet with 3 equalized cams, &lt;em&gt;a la&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href="http://falcon.com/books/9780762782079"&gt;climbing anchors by John Long&lt;/a&gt;. Pay attention
to that black webbing because it's got a bit part in this story later on. I swear
my second has a backup clove hitch on a 4th piece out of the frame you can't see,
so he can escape the belay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Crux Pitch" src="images/P2010028.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's one more sketchy traverse on frictiony slab protected by a single bolt,
and then the rest of Snake Dike is all jugs and 5 easy. You should download the
&lt;a href="http://www.supertopo.com/topos/yosemite/snakedike.pdf"&gt;free supertopo&lt;/a&gt; if you're
serious about climbing Snake Dike. I had tried to memorize it, because there are so
many bolts on this climb that it's easy to either stop early or skip an anchor.
People talk about girth hitching chicken heads but the dike doesn't really take
protection. It's just a long juggy extrusion that you follow like a ladder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike The Dike" src="images/P2010029.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the rest of the pitches are juggy and positive but super runout with just a single
bolt every 60 feet or so. In fact, some of the pitches don't have &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; bolts!
Another interesting twist is that every so often you come across a pair of bolts that
looks like an anchor, but is for shorter ropes. Knowing where to belay is part of route
finding that can speed up your climb and remember, "speed is safety!" Clip the
wrong bolts though, and you might find yourself and your partner simul-climbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Runout Bols" src="images/P2010030.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The climbing was smooth, and the views were spectacular. Take a moment to
appreciate this sweeping vista starting to your left past Glacier Point right
to the valley floor. Is that El Cap off in the distance? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike View L" src="images/P2010034.JPG"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Snake Dike View M" src="images/P2010033.JPG"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Snake Dike View R" src="images/P2010032.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look just a little further to the left though, and you can see what I was seeing.
Dark clouds gathering around Liberty Cap and Mt. Broderick were moving our way. We
needed to pick up the pace, or we would end up with only bad options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Dark Clouds" src="images/P2010036.JPG"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Liberty Cap &amp;amp; Mt. Broderick" src="images/P2010035.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there anything that is purely deterministic? I believe almost every event has
a distribution of possible outcomes, some good, some great, some bad, and some
very bad. Lucky or not, those possibilities aren't usually random, some outcomes
are more likely than others. So now I had to weigh the odds that we could summit
and decend before it start raining. The main danger for climbers in the rain is
lightning. For a quick primer check out this Climbing Magazine article,
&lt;a href="https://www.climbing.com/skills/learn-this-laws-of-lightning/"&gt;Don't Get Struck By Lightning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my haste, I made a tactical error. After clipping a pair of anchor bolts,
I decided to pass them thinking they were for shorter ropes, but before I knew
it I was literally at the end of my rope. I had clipped the bolts between me and
my second, and I knew there was another pair of anchors just up ahead. I felt confident
so I decided to start simul-climbing, and I yelled down to my partner, "START CLIMBING!"
A 60-meter rope is almost 200-ft long, and in the vastness, sounds get blown away, so I
just started yanking on the rope forcing him to follow me upward. This worked for a few
feet but then I was yanked to a stop. I could see the next pair of anchors, but they were
just out of reach. I turned around to start screaming frantic, feeling the buzz
of adrenalin shoot into my veins, when I saw my partner take off his backpack. I was
completely confused. Dread crept into my bones as I saw something flutter off into
the breeze, but I was quickly filled with relief as my partner slung his backpack
and lept upward. I flew to the anchors, clipped them like a baby hugging his mother
and hauled up my parter. "What the heck was that?" I asked as he got closer, and he
explained that he had climbed to the end of that black piece of webbing, but it was
too tight, and he couldn't reach down to unclip the locking carabiner I'd lent him,
so he cut the sling and left the biner. It was a small price I was happy to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Scramble" src="images/P2010037.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mini epic almost over, the rest of the climb was uneventful. We reached the third class
scramble while there were still patches of blue in the cloudy skies, but once on the
summit, while taking victory photos and scarfing food, it started snowing and we
knew we had to sprint down the cables. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Snow" src="images/P2010039.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We reached the bottom and started planning our celebration with cocktails at the
Mountain Bar at the Lodge. There we reflected on the choices we made during the
day as the conditions changed, and we reassessed our risk. Our planning didn't
consider the surprise mini-epic, but a little skill and a lot of luck kept us
safe. I don't think either of us were particularly risky, even before we had kids.
Sure, there's a spectrum, and each person has to make a conscious choice of the
risks they're willing to take, but to do that effectively requires understanding
and evaluating the risk especially as conditions change. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snake Dike Me on the Diving Board" src="images/P2010041.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's me 20 years ago, after that Snake Hike, on the infamous diving board,
overlooking the valley. I reflect back on my climbing experiences, and I realize
that of the many valuable lessons I learned in the mountains, assessing risk
has been one of the most useful. Understanding uncertainty has helped me navigate
an often uncertain world, and to realize that as conditions change, I can re-evaluate
my risk and make different choices. You can too. Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like this Climbing Life Lesson, check out this one on
&lt;a href="https://breakingbytes.github.io/climbing-life-lessons-offwidths.html"&gt;Offwidths&lt;/a&gt; or why it's better to stick
with the plan rather than making last minute changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-notes"&gt;My Notes:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any event has a distribution of possible outcomes, some that are more favorable than others and some that are definitely undesirable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The distribution might not be random, in other words some outcomes might be more likely than others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Risk assessment is a measure of the possibility of favorable and undesirable outcomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each person's or party's tolerance for risk is a choice that depends on trade offs between the chances of favorable vs. undesired outcomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;changing conditions force you to reavaluate the risk and make new choices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes conditions and risk can change quickly, leaving you exposed to greater risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exposure in theoretical terms is a measure of the level risk you've accepted but in practical terms it's measured in how far or long it will take to escape danger and get to help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;climbing in the mountains automatically increases your exposure because it can be difficult to escape the rock safely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;climbing in the backcountry can increase exposure significantly because in addition to a safe retreat you may also need to hike and drive significant distances before you can get help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dangers in the mountains include route finding, getting caught in bad weather, darkness, lightning strikes, equipment failure, missing or losing equipment, falls, injuries, death&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learning to evaluate risk in changing conditions is an important skill that can have practical advantages in all aspects of your life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it can help you tolerate uncertainty, because reality is both full of possiblities and uncertainty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it can help you rule out unlikely or scenarios with no serious consequences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="project-management"></category><category term="project-planning"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="rant"></category><category term="risk-management"></category></entry><entry><title>Case for Experts in Management</title><link href="https://breakingbytes.github.io/case-for-experts-in-management.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Mikofski</name></author><id>tag:breakingbytes.github.io,2021-05-22:/case-for-experts-in-management.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Empathy &amp;amp; a growth mindset are equally important to both managers &amp;amp; individual contributors.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="a-case-for-more-experts-in-management"&gt;A Case for More Experts in Management&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="intro"&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, let me say I don't think you need to be an expert to be a good manager. In fact, I don't even think you need to be an expert to be a good individual contributor. Sure it helps, but I believe there are other traits that are more important for making good technical contributions and better management decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mentor once told me, when hiring, look for intelligence versus skillset, because a fast &amp;amp; flexible learner continues to be useful when a project ends, but a finite skillset will eventually be obsolete. My definition of intelligence has evolved, and now I think he was really talking about mindsets. I believe having empathy &amp;amp; a growth mindset might be even more important than expertise or leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="maximize-diversity"&gt;Maximize Diversity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, there's a common misconception that experts lack leadership skills, or that their unique skills are better utilized as individual contributors. However, this artificial perception blocks potential contributions from others with unique perspectives, and it creates a void of subject matter expertise &amp;amp; experience in leadership. Instead it reinforces the stereotype of the alpha-type boss and the nerdy, absent minded professor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Morty the mad scientist stereotype" src="images/morty-back-to-future.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly feel this lack of diversity in leadership &amp;amp; individual contributions is a real missed opportunity to maximize collaboration with unique voices &amp;amp; special experiences across an organization. This opportunity cost limits growth and sustainability, and I would bet these types of businesses die from starvation &amp;amp; cannibalism as experts give up, frustrated from a lack of voice, and leaders, failing to listen to these valuable perspectives, opt for short term gains and cash out before they crash &amp;amp; burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="a-new-model"&gt;A New Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of perpetuating this rigid 20th century hierarchy, I propose a new model where empathy &amp;amp; open mindedness are championed for all, and opportunities are encouraged for all maximizing diversity. If a contributor excels at research or analysis, that doesn't mean they can't learn to be an empathic leader. If their work is a safe &amp;amp; supportive environment that encourages stretch goals and embraces failure instead of punishing it, they can grow to accomplish anything, enhancing their perspectives and adding value to the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, why are non-technical workers pushed into management, limiting their opportunities to learn new skills and make unique contributions. I don't believe workers are just one thing and only have one value. They are constantly growing and bringing new values to the organization. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="t-shapes-growth-mindsets"&gt;T-Shapes &amp;amp; Growth Mindsets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several reports have expressed the importance of lateral moves and T-shaped workers [&lt;a href="#references"&gt;1-4&lt;/a&gt;]. When a manager takes an assignment as an individual contributor they learn new skills and gain new perspectives that gives them both depth &amp;amp; breadth in their field. This allows them to synthesize new ideas and innovations they wouldn't have had if they'd remained siloed. Similarly when experts take on the responsibility of management, they are forced to delegate work, give up control, &amp;amp; learn the business constraints that limit what the organization can do. These perspectives are critical. Again, as with the manager, the expert now synthesizes these new ideas and innovates in ways they wouldn't have if they'd stayed in the lab. Both of these coworkers are now T-shaped. Instead of staying in fixed roles, by embracing a growth mindset, they have created synergy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what &lt;a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/carol-dweck"&gt;Carol Dweck&lt;/a&gt; was encouraging when she wrote about motivation in her 2006 book &lt;em&gt;Mindset: The New Psychology of Success&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href="#references"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Fixed-mindset individuals dread failure because it is a negative statement on their basic abilities, while growth mindset individuals don't mind or fear failure as much because they realize their performance can be improved and learning comes from failure." &lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carol_Dweck#Mindset_work"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="empathy"&gt;Empathy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy is always in short supply,  although we all know it to be the most valuable of human abilities. Would anyone of us be alive if it weren't for the caring love of our family &amp;amp; friends. At work we draw boundaries, as we should, but that should not exclude empathy from the workplace. In fact, I argue it's even more important. You want people to give their best, then they have to have a safe &amp;amp; supportive environment where they feel trusted and respected. No punitive action is ever useful at work. Positive &amp;amp; constructive feedback is based on the assumption of good faith. That everyone is pulling together and giving their best for mutual success. Where failure is not criticized, but a learning opportunity for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in summary, don't box yourself in or your coworkers. Strive to create a culture where anything is possible, learning is continuous, and failure is always an option, and that's good. Encourage lateral moves and grow a T-shaped workforce. Listen to experts and encourage them step outside of their comfort zone to take a turn at the wheel, while leaders experiment and analyze data. Don't be afraid to mix it up. The result might be a more sustainable and profitable business. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2001/03/introducing-t-shaped-managers-knowledge-managements-next-generation"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introducing T-Shaped Managers: Knowledge Management’s Next Generation&lt;/strong&gt; -- Morten T. Hansen &amp;amp; Bolko von Oetinger, Harvard Business Review, 2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://hbr.org/podcast/2018/05/lateral-moves"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lateral Moves&lt;/strong&gt; -- Dear HBR Podcast, Harvard Business Review, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/value-t-shaped-people-mitchell-platt"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Value of T-Shaped People&lt;/strong&gt; -- Mitchell Pratt, LinkedIn, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/say-yes-lateral-move-you-marissa-lee"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To Say Yes or No: Is a Lateral Move for You?&lt;/strong&gt; -- Marissa Lee, LinkedIn, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/44330/mindset-by-carol-s-dweck-phd/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mindset: The New Psychology of Success&lt;/em&gt;, Carol Dweck, Penguin Random House, 2007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2016/01/what-having-a-growth-mindset-actually-means"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Having a “Growth Mindset” Actually Means&lt;/strong&gt; -- Carol Dweck, Harvard Business Review, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/education/archive/2016/12/how-praise-became-a-consolation-prize/510845/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Praise Became a Consolation Prize:
Helping children confront challenges requires a more nuanced understanding of the “growth mindset.”&lt;/strong&gt; -- Christine Gross-Loh
, The Atlantic, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="project-management"></category><category term="rant"></category></entry><entry><title>Climbing Life Lessons: Offwidths</title><link href="https://breakingbytes.github.io/climbing-life-lessons-offwidths.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Mikofski</name></author><id>tag:breakingbytes.github.io,2021-05-01:/climbing-life-lessons-offwidths.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An offwidth is a difficult climb, too big for hand jams, but too small to chimney.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="life-lessons-from-an-offwidth"&gt;Life Lessons from an Offwidth&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="East Buttress" src="images/eastbutress-of-elcap-route.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.supertopo.com/rock-climbing/Yosemite-Valley-El-Capitan-East-Buttress"&gt;East Buttress of El Capitan&lt;/a&gt; is one of the best but hardest climbs I've ever been on. It's long &amp;amp; sustained, with huge exposure &amp;amp; beautiful, sweeping views of the valley &amp;amp; Middle Cathedral. In typical Yosemite fashion, it challenges you right from the get go with a steep chimney overlooking a 1,000-foot drop. Then on the 9th pitch, after you've been climbing for a few hours, over 2,000 feet above the valley floor, there's a classic Yosemite offwidth. Like glacial polish, Yosemite offwidths are a ritual you can't avoid. You just have to stash your ego, open your heart, and humbly listen to what the great mother is trying to teach you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="pitch 9 offwidth" src="images/9-ow-pitcheastbut2.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's me, 20 years ago, on that incredible, unforgettable flaring 9th pitch. An offwidth is a difficult climb. It's too big for hand jams, but too small to chimney. Everybody has advice for offwidths: armbars, heel-toe jams, chicken wings, kneebars, shoulder jams, handstacks, liebacks, you name it. About the only advice worth following comes from climbing and squirrel suit legend &lt;a href="https://stephdavis.co/blog/how-to-climb-offwidths-101/"&gt;Steph Davis&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the biggest thing with offwidths is to remain calm and be patient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She makes it sound so easy! However, there's another dimension that exponentially increases the challenge. Placing protection on offwidths is no joke. First, it's no fun lugging a giant cam 1,000 vertical feet just to use it once. Oh, did I mention the 9th pitch is one of the longest? So make that two huge 5-inch cams. So far we have challenging, sustained, strenuous technique combined with sketchy, runout pro, fatigue, and huge exposure. Oh, but did I mention the breathtaking, awe-inspiring views? Look right across the yawning expanse of the valley is the mighty Middle Cathedral rock! And behold Half Dome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Middle Cathedral" src="images/mighty-cathedral-in-the-morn.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Half Dome" src="images/halfdomefromelcap.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling good now? So what exactly is the great mother trying to teach us? Trust. Relax. Move intentionally, methodically, and don't hesitate. Above all, resist the urge to bump or reposition your pro. What's this? Remember we only have one gigantic cam with us on this slog, we're scared and tired, so it might seem logical to reach down and pull that cam up, or maybe you spy the perfect placement you couldn't find when you shoved it in desperately thinking you might slip out any second. Sometimes if you're lucky on a nice evenly spaced marathon, maybe you can bump the cam over your head a few times as you move up. However, these dream parallel chasms only exist in Canyonland sandstone. Out on the granite cliffs of the valley, unfortunately you're more likely to accidentally lose your only last good pro as the cam tips out into a sudden widening or jam in the back never to be retrieved again. Your second will curse you, other parties will praise you as they clip this fixed pro, and later a seasoned YOSAR regular will pull it out as the rock changes, reading it like an ancient magic rune. A &lt;a href="https://www.climbing.com/skills/learn-this-offwidth-protection-primer/"&gt;Climbing magazine&lt;/a&gt; primer summarizes the cons well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the cam tips out or falls down the rope, you could end up way above your last piece. Worse, it could knock out that last piece—and possibly your belayer. Be careful not to push your cam into a spot that’s too tight, too tipped out to hold a fall, or out of your reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course use long slings so you don't inadvertently walk your cam out of its spot, and suffer the same fate as if you bumped it yourself. Argh! There are so many things to consider, and you're in a really tight spot (pun intended). So don't try any 11th hour dramatics. Leave the gear where it is, keep moving, find another placement deeper in the crack, maybe back it up. Climbers have an old saying that is part cheek and part truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When in doubt run it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It means keep climbing. Unless you're going to downclimb or retreat, it's better to keep making forward progress, than to burn out in a precarious situation. Chances are you will power through the moves, and more often than not the rock offers you a neat solution that saves your ass in the nick of time. But you won't have the juice to make those moves, or the brains to read what the rock is telling you, if you spin out trying to fix a piece of pro that's already your best placement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's the lesson? How does this apply to me, in my office, clicking a keyboard? Have you ever had a project or a product that's about to ship? And your boss calls you at 11pm, and says, "Hey change this thing." Or maybe you're the boss, and you call your team with a desperate hail Mary pitch at the last minute. &lt;strong&gt;Don't. Just. Don't!&lt;/strong&gt; Calm down. Relax. Trust your team. Stick to the plan. The most important part is sending the project. Whatever your idea is, it's just not worth it. Or maybe it is? But you better be damned sure, because you had a product ready to ship. Are you certain you really want to fuck it up on a Friday night? Why not sleep on it? Maybe in the morning, when you start getting feedback, some bad, some good, on the product that you &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; delivered, you'll be glad that you didn't almost bomb everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the lesson. After the 9th pitch, the climbing on the East Buttress was still hard, not technically, but we had reached the end of our rope (no pun this time), and we were fried. There was some mundane 5-easy, exposed traversing with awful rope drag, but we made it to the top. And what a top out it was. Half Dome ablaze in the most glorious sunset of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="sunset over half dome" src="images/redhalfdome.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The descent is actually the most dangerous part of the climb. Something like 70% of climbing accidents actually happen when parties rap off the ends of their ropes, because they're too tired to pay attention to tiny but crucial details. We descended the famed East Ledges which true El Cap warriors rap from when they finish big wall test pieces like the Nose. There were fixed ropes that looked good enough, and we stuck the finish, with an elated sense of the sublime. The great mother had graced us with her wisdom, and we had tried our best to suss it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So maybe that's the lesson? To keep it all in perspective? We had planned this trip, read the guides, studied the topo maps, racked our gear with intent, rose early and given it our best. We were lucky that we didn't have to improvise. We were given a cake walk, and we ate it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for listening. Here's me right before the crux 10b move after the chimney. Not a care in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="at the 10b crux after the chimney" src="images/marcoatchimneypitch.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="agile"></category><category term="project-management"></category><category term="project-planning"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="rant"></category><category term="time-management"></category></entry><entry><title>Iterative Project Planning in Research and Development</title><link href="https://breakingbytes.github.io/iterative-project-planning-in-research-and-development.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-16T13:04:39-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-16T13:04:39-07:00</updated><author><name>Mark Mikofski</name></author><id>tag:breakingbytes.github.io,2017-06-16:/iterative-project-planning-in-research-and-development.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Iterative planning is a a successful strategy for research and development.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="objectives-and-scope"&gt;Objectives and Scope&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this document is to outline a successful strategy for the optimal
preparation, execution and measurement of plans for open-ended research and
development projects. In particular this document demonstrates the effective use
of short-term iteration cycle planning commonly known as Agile, Scrum or Kanban
project management. It is important to note that the methods described in this
document are not applicable to projects which have well-known execution times
such as engineering, procurement and construction (EPC). Also while short-term
iteration cycle planning may work well for open-ended research questions, they
may be combined with traditional waterfall techniques in time-limited projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="methods"&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, an iterative project plan has these major features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="mission"&gt;Mission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All projects should have a big giant overriding mission statement. This is what
you look at when you're really lost and trying to re-inspire your team. In other
words, this is what it's all about. For example a school projects mission might
be the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To empower students to become agents of their own learning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="goals-or-objectives"&gt;Goals or Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to accomplish the mission, you need a few long-term, broad goals or
objectives that point out what direction you think you need to follow. Don't be
too specific here. Continuing the school environment example, some goals might
be the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engage students in STEAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reinforce literacy in every interaction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a strong sense of community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="release-cycle"&gt;Release Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick a long-term time frame to work in, during which you hope to make progress
in the same direction as these goals. This is your "release cycle". For example
in a school setting the release cycle might be every three months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="milestones-or-epics"&gt;Milestones or Epics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Narrow down milestones for each of the broad goals that you think can be
accomplished during each release cycle. These milestones are sometimes called
"epics" or "projects"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="iteration-cycle"&gt;Iteration Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick a short-term iteration cycle during which you can meet with your team and
measure progress on your "epics". Iteration cycles vary anywhere from weekly to
monthly, but a good compromise is every two weeks. This time-frame is your
"iteration" or "scrum" because you will often meet your group for a quick tally
kind of like a rugby scrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tasks"&gt;Tasks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brainstorm the detailed, small, atomic tasks that you think would be required to
complete the epics and put them on cards in a list called your backlog. There
are many online tools like &lt;a href="https://trello.com/"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; that are designed to
make this easy, but a large cork board works just fine. An atomic task is nearly
the smallest discreet unit of work you can think of that would need to be done
in order to accomplish the milestone. Tasks are easily measured, and it should
also be easier to predict the time necessary to complete them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="effort"&gt;Effort&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assign each card or task an effort score. Keep the scale small; think of it as a
rubric, not a linear scale, but it could loosely be proportional to time. A
common effort scale might be the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Effort&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;chore&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;any known length of time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;easy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt; 1 day&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;hard&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt; 1 week&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mini-epic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;gt; 1 week&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually a chore is a well-defined task that is done all the time so you know
exactly how long it takes. Just mark chores on your schedule and do them. A
mini-epic probably means you should break it into smaller tasks, but you may try
to do it as a single task anyway. Effort is used to measure progress; the data
is used to normalize and prioritize future iteration cycles. Since any data is
useful as long as it is carefully measured and calibrated, you may adjust your
effort scale to fit your needs after several iterations and releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="kanban"&gt;Kanban&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kanban, Scrum and Agile have many similarities. See this
&lt;a href="https://www.smartsheet.com/agile-vs-scrum-vs-waterfall-vs-kanban"&gt;Smartsheet article for a side-by-side comparison&lt;/a&gt;.
In a nutshell, Agile is a philosophy, while Scrum and Kanban are
implementations of Agile. Scrum introduces the concept of a sprint or interval
while Kanban introduces puts all tasks into lists or swimlanes on a board that
everyone can see and manipulate. IMO forget the names and concentrate of what
works best and is easiest to use. The goal is to be efficient and productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest Kanban board can be divided into 3 swimlanes, which is the default
workflow for a new Trello board:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To do (&lt;em&gt;aka&lt;/em&gt; backlog)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing (&lt;em&gt;aka&lt;/em&gt; current work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Done (&lt;em&gt;aka&lt;/em&gt; completed work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can add more swimlanes to capture other items such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;wishlist, icebox or parking lot - items for a rainy day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;won't do - items ruled out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in review - almost done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on deck - in between backlog and current work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="pomodoro"&gt;Pomodoro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One aspect of an iterative workflow that can create anxiety is the measurement
of progress and the evaluation or prediction of the time to complete a task or
milestone. The
&lt;a href="https://cirillocompany.de/pages/pomodoro-technique"&gt;Pomodoro Technique&lt;/a&gt; is a
time management method from the 1980's that provides a concrete conversion rate
between units of work and units of time. One pomodoro is typically equivalent to
30-minutes. Using the Pomodoro technique is a diagnostic tool that eliminates
the need to normalize burndown rates since converting between pomodoros and time
is not subjective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="trello-and-pomello"&gt;Trello and Pomello&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trello is an online tool that offers a Kanban-esque board to organize tasks and
iterations. The &lt;a href="http://www.pomelloapp.com/"&gt;Pomello app&lt;/a&gt; is a plugin for Trello
that integrates Pomodoro. It logs time on task, measures the number of pomodoros
spent on a task and lets you move completed tasks to their swimlane when done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="current-work-option-1-kanban"&gt;Current Work (Option 1: Kanban)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my personal preference because IMO the workflow is much simpler since
there are only 3 swimlanes. I use this with the Pomodoro Technique. At the
beginning of each iteration, pull cards into the current work list and count
the number of pomodoros used on each. When a task is done, move it to the
"completed"  list and pull a new item from the backlog. That's it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="current-iteration-option-2-scrum"&gt;Current Iteration (Option 2: Scrum)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note this method won't work with Pomello, it's better to use
&lt;a href="http://scrumfortrello.com/"&gt;Scrum for Trello&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://www.burndownfortrello.com/"&gt;Burndown for Trello&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of each iteration cycle move some cards from the backlog into a
new list called your current iteration. Iterations may be numbered or identified
by date or work-week as long as they are recorded. You should assign individuals
or small teams to tasks and encourage frequent communication and collaboration
between individuals and teams during the iteration. During the iteration teams
and individuals should measure their progress by deducting points from the
initial effort of each task until they are complete and the remaining effort is
zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the iteration communicate with your team frequently and make adjustments
as needed. For example, during an iteration you might do any or all of the
following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take new cards from the back log as needed until the iteration is over.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reorder cards on the backlog or current iteration board to reprioritize.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose tasks based on their estimated effort and the remaining time in the iteration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reclassify a tasks as an epic and break it into to subtasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reassign individuals and teams to tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="burndown-scrum"&gt;Burndown (Scrum)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the iteration, tally up the effort points completed, add it to the
previous total and divide by the total number of iterations. Plot this data for
everyone, for individuals, for all iterations cumulatively and for each
iteration. These are your burndown rates. Use them to normalize team members and
to determine how much effort can be accomplished per iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="table-1-example-effort-per-iteration"&gt;Table 1: Example Effort per Iteration&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Iteration&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bobby&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Sally&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Juan&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Briana&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Effort&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id="table-2-example-cummulative-effort"&gt;Table 2: Example Cummulative Effort&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Iteration&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bobby&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Sally&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Juan&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Briana&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Cummulative&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id="table-3-example-burndown-calculation"&gt;Table 3: Example Burndown Calculation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Iteration&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Bobby&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Sally&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Juan&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Briana&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Average&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.125&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.625&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the burndown rates and cumulative effort you can make several
observations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bobby and Briana are either the team’s top performers or are over estimating
  effort. Use this info to normalize the team by either using your own effort
  scale or pairing teammates together to see their joint effort estimates. For
  example if Briana is high performer, her burndown stands, and if Bobby’s
  performance is more equivalent to the team average then adjust it by a factor
  of around 85% to 7.65 instead of 9. Ditto for Sally if she is sandbagging her
  effort estimates, adjust hers by a factor of 1.7x to 7.65.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now that your burndown is normalized, the adjusted team average is around
  8 points of Effort per Iteration. Therefore you should only plan to add tasks
  summing up to around 32 effort points each iteration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your iteration is half over, and Juan’s queue is empty, you can only expect
  him to deliver around 4 effort in the remaining time, so choose tasks summing
  up to this or less.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reprioritization"&gt;Reprioritization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After calculating burndown your team can reprioritize tasks and epics, both in
response to data on progress but also due to a shift in the team mission and
associated objectives. Move incomplete tasks from the current iteration either
to epics because they were just too big to do in a single iteration, back to the
backlog because you over allocated effort or to a board called the “Icebox” or
“Parking Lot” to revisit on a rainy day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="release"&gt;Release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the release, publish what you have. Report on it. Re-evaluate your
milestones and compare to your broad long term goals and your mission.  Adjust
your milestones as needed. Then celebrate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some typical workflows and how you can set them up using Trello.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="kanban_1"&gt;Kanban&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just take the default Trello layout and start working. Put ideas that come up
into the backlog. Break them up into tasks as needed. Each week move some items
into the current work list. When an item is finished move it to the completed
list. Use the Pomello app to measure how many pomodoros they take, and use that
info to make predictions about when projects will get done. That's it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="scrum"&gt;Scrum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to use Trello for Scrum is to set up 4 boards:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backlog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Current Iteration by date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Icebox&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each iteration, I archive the old iteration and create a new iteration board
with the date. I move cards around all the time. I only assign effort to tasks
in the backlog which get dragged to the current iteration. I create links from
tasks to epics and vice-versa. I put lots of comments on the cards as I make
progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="rationale"&gt;Rationale&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many arguments for using short-term iteration cycle planning. I will
list the major salient points here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="uncertainty-is-hyperbolic"&gt;Uncertainty is Hyperbolic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research and development projects are inherently unknowns. There may be some
data that indicates around doing small isolated tasks, but predicting a string
of tasks and how they will proceed from one another is not possible because as
predictions move out of the data centroid and extrapolate to larger projects and
longer time-frames the uncertainty explodes hyperbolically. Therefore better
predictions can only be made close to the data centroid centered on small atomic
tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="humans-are-meta-cognitively-wired"&gt;Humans are Meta Cognitively Wired&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta cognition is understanding about how we think, and we know a lot about how
we think we work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="we-get-a-rush-from-checking-off-tasks-dopamine"&gt;We get a rush from checking off tasks. (Dopamine)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using iterative project planning with shorter term iterations allows
contributors to feel more sense of accomplishment because they complete more
tasks, they receive recognition for completed work and have a clear sense of
expectations because data is explicit and meaningful. The feeling comes from
dopamine released each time we tick off a task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="we-dislike-wasted-effort-endorphins"&gt;We dislike wasted effort. (Endorphins)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only tasks are S.M.A.R.T.  Milestones, objectives and mission statements are
only loosely structured allowing teams to concentrate on the task at hand. By
spending less time planning out long-term objectives teams feel a strong sense
of purpose. Nothing is more aggravating than spending a long time planning
something only to have it switched around completely halfway through it. This
frustration leads ultimately to burnout and dysfunction. The corollary to this
is the excitement and morale boost of diving into work quickly and quickly
scoring small victories. Even a few small failures here are seen as positive
data toward the correct course of action because there isn’t a lot riding on
them. Working hard releases endorphins, which soothes anxiety and makes us feel
accomplished. A lack of endorphins however leads to anger and stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="we-are-more-productive-when-we-feel-self-directed-and-that-our-work-has-purpose-serotonin"&gt;We are more productive when we feel self-directed and that our work has purpose. (Serotonin)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iterative project planning allows teams to be more productive with less oversite
since they participate in creating tasks and their current workload by taking
tasks from the backlog. Also by leverage Agile project management software to
organize tasks in iterations and calculate burndown, companies can allow
management to focus on the “Big Picture” giving the entire organization a
stronger sense of unity and focus. This sense of purpose and self-value comes
from serotonin released as we partake in planning our own work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="we-like-to-work-in-groups-oxytocin"&gt;We like to work in groups. (Oxytocin)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iterative project planning is inherently designed for groups. Working together
on a project build trust intimacy and ultimately synergy which multiply
productivity. Understanding and valuing each other’s strengths and weaknesses
makes us closer even in a professional setting. This releases oxytocin which
makes us feel appreciated and loved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IMHO iterative project planning is a no brainer for any research and development
group. It increases productivity while reducing costs by leveraging more
individual contributors and sharing leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="links"&gt;Links&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia Articles and Perspectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/OptimizeForTinyVictories.aspx"&gt;Optimize for tiny victories - Scott Hanselman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://pragdave.me/blog/2014/03/04/time-to-kill-agile.html"&gt;Agile is dead - Pragma Dave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agile_management"&gt;Agile Mangement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agile_software_development"&gt;Agile Software Development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agile_software_development"&gt;Scrum (software development)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban_(development)"&gt;Kanban (development)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online Tools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://trello.com/markmikofski/recommend"&gt;Trello planning tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pomelloapp.com/"&gt;Pomello app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://scrumfortrello.com/"&gt;scrumfortrello&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.burndownfortrello.com/"&gt;burndownfortrello&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gantt-chart.com/"&gt;ganttify for Trello&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.pivotaltracker.com/"&gt;Pivotal Tracker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://redbooth.com/"&gt;Redbooth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="agile"></category><category term="kanban"></category><category term="scrum"></category><category term="development"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="time-management"></category><category term="project-management"></category><category term="project-planning"></category></entry></feed>